Guide to the Justin S. Morrill papers, 1814-1937, 1982.
Morrill, Justin S. papers, 1814-1937, 1982.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Justin S. Morrill papers, 1814-1937, 1982.
1146
Justin S. Morrill, 1810-1898.
3.3 cubic ft.
Correspondence, drafts of speeches, pamphlets and other printed material, scrapbooks, photographs, and other personal items.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Correspondence, drafts of speeches, pamphlets and other printed material, mainly relating to the Civil War and Reconstruction, the status of freed blacks, the tariff and international trade, passage of the Land Grant College Act, and other public questions.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Justin S. Morrill was a congressman and financier.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Correspondence, drafts of speeches, pamphlets and other printed material, mainly relating to the Civil War and Reconstruction, the status of freed blacks, the tariff and international trade, passage of the Land Grant College Act, and other public questions; scrapbook containing a photocopy of Morrill's Wanderings and Scribblings, or A Journal of a Journey South and West in May, June and July, A.D. 1841; a scrapbook of obituary notices; a scrapbook and other items relating to the 75th anniversary of the Land Grant College Act, 1937; and photographs and other personal items. Correspondents include George T. Brown, Schuyler Colfax, John H. Freeman, James A. Garfield, Horace Greeley, Benjamin Harrison, Rutherford B. Hayes, William Dean Howells, Nellie Grant Sartoris, Jacob Gould Schurman, John Sherman, Horatio King (who wrote letters to Morrill on his birthday), A. D. White and President Grover Cleveland.
Note: Item lists of letters and speeches are available in the accession folder.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Morrill, Justin S. (Justin Smith), 1810-1898.; Cleveland, Grover, 1837-1908.; Colfax, Schuyler, 1823-1885.; Garfield, James A. (James Abram), 1831-1881.; Greeley, Horace, 1811-1872.; Harrison, Benjamin, 1833-1901.; Hayes, Rutherford Birchard, 1822-1893.; Howells, William Dean, 1837-1920.; King, Horatio King, 1811-1897.; Schurman, Jacob Gould, 1854-1942.; Sherman, John.; White, Andrew Dickson, 1832-1918.
Subjects:
Afro-Americans.; Commerce.; Freedmen.; Education--New York (State); School lands.; Tariff.; Voyages and travels.; Legislators--United States.
Places:
United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.
Form and Genre Terms:
Obituaries.; Photographs.; Scrapbooks.; Speeches.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
CONTAINER LIST
- Link to a PDF finding aid with more detailed information about the contents of the collection.
- Speech drafts, 1828-1839 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Sermon, speech drafts, 1840-1849 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Speech drafts, 1850-1859 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Correspondence; "On Agriculture, delivered at Woodstock, Vt.", Sept. 27th, 1860 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- "Address at St. Johnsbury, Vt. on the Culture of Man and some of the requisite means.", 1860 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Speech, notes, Act (H.R. 338), 1861 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Letter (extract), trade circular, Act (H.R. 312), 1862 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Correspondence, Act (H.R. 592), drafts, notes, 1862 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Correspondence, notes, newspaper clippings, 1863-1864 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Correspondence, newspaper clippings, address, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Correspondence, newspaper clippings, "Report of ... on The National Statuary Hall", address, 1866 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Correspondence, drafts, report, 1867-1869 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Correspondence, newspaper clipping, address, 1870-1872 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, addresses, newspaper clipping, 1873 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Speech on National Colleges, 1873 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Circular, pamphlets, address, report, annual report, 1874 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Correspondence, circulars, pamphlets, newspaper clippings, address annual reports, 1875-1877 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  Includes letter from A. D. White.
- Bill (H.R. 3544), speech, Correspondence, comparison of receipts and expenditures, 1878-1879 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Correspondence, "Catalogue of the Private Library of Justin S. Morrill", notes, Act (H.R. 4592), 1880-1881 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- January-April: Correspondence, 1882 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- May-December: Correspondence, tariff tract, speech, 1882 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Correspondence, newspaper clippings, drafts and Remarks, 1883 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Jan.-Apr.: Correspondence, Statement, 1884 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Aug.-Dec.: Correspondence, speeches, 1884 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, "Remarks on the Death of General Grant," speech, 1885-1886 Mar. (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Apr.-Dec.: Correspondence, newspaper clipping, poem, telegram, 1886 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Jan.-Aug., undated: Correspondence, address, "Commemorative Addresses. 1862-1887. Massachusetts Agricultural College.", 1887 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  Includes letter from President Grover Cleveland from the Executive Mansion as well as letters from Frances Cleveland..
- Correspondence, addresses, political tract, 1888-1889 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Correspondence, including letter from President Harrison (signed), newspaper clippings, remarks, Congressional Record, poem, 1890-1891 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  Includes letter from Benjamin Harrison
- Correspondence, Resolution (S.R. 24), poem, newspaper clippings, article, Bills (S. 553, 572, 1280), address, pamphlet, 1892-1893 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- January-June: Correspondence, Bill (S. 1460), Resolution (S.R. 62), Amendment (S. 341), poem, remarks, Bill (S. 2135), 1894 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- July-December: Correspondence, Tariff Act, address, 1894 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Correspondence, Bill (S.2569), poems, newspaper clippings, remarks, 1895 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, newspaper clippings, poems, speeches, 1896 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, newspaper clippings, Bill (S.1876), remarks, 1897-1899 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Correspondence, newspaper clippings, The Vermonter, The American Magazine, 1900-1910 Apr. 15 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Correspondence, Apr. 16, 1910-1912 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Tariff and Foreign Trade - copies, rough drafts, and notes for speeches (Box 4, Folder 6-10)
- Hawaiian Islands: Clayton-Bulwer Treaty of 1850 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Party Platform and Records (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Education and Schools (Box 5, Folder 3-4)
- Fine Arts and Architecture address (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Notes and speeches, miscellany (Box 5, Folder 6-11)
- 15 photographs of Morrill and family (Box 6, Folder 0)
- Business, Labor, Industry (Box 6, Folder 1-2)
- Biographical Materials of J. S. Morrill and Colleagues (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Gold and Silver Question; Revenue and Taxation (Box 6, Folder 4-7)
- Gold and Silver Question; Revenue and Taxation (Box 7)
- Photographs (Box 8)
- Genealogy notebook (Box 8)
- Impeachment tickets, 1868 (Box 8)
- Petitions (Box 8)
- Bill (Box 8)
- Notebook (Box 8)
- Miscellaneous family papers (Box 8)
  Includes Brigham Young autograph
- Ruth S. Morrill funeral service, 1898 (Box 8)
- Receipts (Box 8)
- Calling cards (Box 8)
- Mounted clippings (Box 8)
- Key to Justin Morrill's Senate Desk, 1897 (Box 9, Folder 0)
- Cornell University Class of 1884 "Morrill Memorial Medal", 1884 (Box 9, Folder 1)
- Proceedings of the Association of American Colleges and Agricultural Expermient Stations, 1899 (Box 9, Folder 2)
- Land Grant College Radio Hour, Aug. 19, 1936 (Box 9, Folder 3)
- "Energy and Vision" by S.P. Langley, 1888 (Box 9, Folder 4)
- Clippings (Box 9, Folder 5-6)
- Smithsonian Institution certificate signed by Tiffany and Co. (Box 9, Folder 7)
- Portfolio (Box 9, Folder 8)
- Leather (Box 9, Folder 9)
- Scrapbook "Wanderings and Scribblings", 1841 (Box 10)
- Publications by and pertaining to Morrill (Box 11)